Fast. At the beginning of the seventies. That just disappeared later.
As I said, when I was in the military
I found out that I wasn't even allowed to become a non-commissioned officer.
Unless it was for bravery in the face of the enemy. Why? Because of what?
Because of my, uh-uh-uh, because I was a so-called quarter Jew.
And how did you feel when you heard that? Uh, as a second-class person.
Basically
it took me years after the war to get rid of these feelings of inferiority that it gave me.
And a lot of my activities later on were basically an attempt to prove that I could achieve something after all and that I wasn't inferior
as people tried to make me believe at the time. Mhm.
And how did you overcome that? How did I overcome that? Yes.
That's not so easy to answer. It grew-- I gradually grew out of it-- Mhm.
-Later I felt that I was accepted by others and that I could achieve and do something.
Hm, hm. And back then you spoke to your mother and your brother.
Are we inferior - are we inferior? Is this ideology, is it the truth?
Wh-- How...
Were you very influenced by this new ideology, racial science and so on?
Uh, in terms of racial studies, I was against, uh
what was said in the Third Reich right from the start. Mhm.
But, uh, these military successes, that's what impressed me as a boy, uh, uh.
Mhm.
And the, uh, conversations with my parents were always such that they were, uh, against the Nazis.
And so were my brother and I.
But of course we weren't allowed to let them notice us.
Nevertheless, as I said, we weren't completely uninfluenced.
We were in an intermediate position. Mmm.
We were still too young to see through it. Mhm.
I was seventeen at the end of the war.
I didn't have my eighteenth birthday until I was an American prisoner of war
and then I was released at the beginning of forty-six, as an eighteen-year-old.
Why didn't you try to forge your papers?
Why didn't your mother actually try that?
Uh, because my grandfather was very well known and respected as a doctor in Karlsruhe.
And because it was known that he was Jewish, she would have had no chance of forging it.
I know about, uh, this father, this Melitta, um, they obviously managed to keep it secret.
Apparently none of these five, uh, siblings knew that the father was Jewish.
Hmm. But with your case, that was quite different. Yes.
And so in the military, at the draft. Yes.
Did you have to declare that you weren't pure Aryan? No.
So how did that come out? How did people find out about it?
And was the camaraderie in the military good?
Uh, that's actually one of the most valuable things I experienced in human terms back then.
You get to know people. (laughs softly) Mhm.
You see who can't be influenced by something like that and who takes you seriously as a person and comrade (clears throat).
Mhm.
And others who behaved more or less contemptuously or who withdrew because they thought
uh, if I have closer contact with him, it could harm me.
My parents often told me about old acquaintances who, uh, in 1933
from one day to the next
no longer greeted them on the street or no longer knew them.
And, uh, I grew up with this knowledge back then and also experienced it myself
because some people withdrew and others didn't.
But at least I experienced one positive case.
It was during the war when a teacher, who now knew, er
that my grandfather was Jewish, said to my brother and me: "Go outside
I want to talk to the class." And then he, he was a party member
but he wasn't on the inside, he was only on the outside.
And then he took the class and said: "What can they do about it?
Take them in, let them be comrades, just like you." I gave the man a lot of credit for that.
And did your, yes, student comrades actually do that?
One of them objected at the time. And, uh, they...
We noticed that, uh, not all of them, but some of them did behave a bit, uh
more comradely towards us.
But through what, yes, through a what member, you say, right? Yes.
That actually gave you the feeling, didn't it? Still pity, sorry.
Through pity, you would say, wouldn't you? Because they were ordered, actually.
Yes, yes, yes. But there was still a certain restraint.
People were no longer aggressive when I said that, some others were nevertheless, but passive.
But as I said, a few who did were completely impartial and friendly.
And you really appreciate that.
When Hitler came to the market, what did your parents tell you later about this
yes, grasp of the market? Were your parents, were you very influenced by it?
Were you influenced by Hitler?
Did you think that Hitler was our man for the future?
My mother was strongly opposed from the beginning until the end.
My father, like many men of that generation, was probably a bit more nationalistic.
Not in a partisan sense, but that which is German is good and right
roughly in terms of this attitude. And that's why he had a different attitude
even though he was well aware of all the terrible things that were going on.
But there were areas where he also admired the fact that unemployment was getting better
for example, that France was overrun so quickly in the French campaign.
That made him happy at the time. But what about the boys, yes? Yes.
His boys too? Yes, yes.
I was also influenced by this back then and I was happy too.
Did anyone try to persuade your father to perhaps divorce his wife or leave his wife because of his Jewish ancestry?
I don't know about that. That was me... I don't know.
My father and mother had a good marriage.
I don't think they ever thought of anything like that.
I only found out later that if my mother had died
she wouldn't have been allowed to be buried in the usual cemetery because she was half-Jewish.
I don't know where she would have had to be buried.
There was obviously a decree at the time that forbade that.
And was it just you and your brothers who were so-called Mischlinge in that class?
Did you get to know any other so-called half-breeds? Not in my class.
I did have one classmate in elementary school who was Jewish.
They then emigrated. A half-Jew, also a so-called half-Jew.
And later at grammar school we were the only ones.
I only remember one who was one class below me.
He had to leave grammar school in the early forties.
He was half, yes, to whom a brother and I were a quarter. What was his name?
Klaus Hermann, Dr. Klaus Hermann. He was a lawyer and, uh, came after the war
took the entrance exam for my class and we did our A-levels together.
I think he was also in Theresienstadt. And, well.
Can you quickly retell this story about your aunt and this Aryanization?
It's very interesting. Yes.
And when did you - can you say when you found out about it?
I learned about it during the war. Okay. My mother's sister. What was her name?
Renate Schiller at the time.
Um, she worked as a nurse during the war and was with a man who gave her a daughter.
The man was deployed on the Eastern Front. What was his name? Ludwig Eitel.
The marriage was subsequently declared as a marriage.
That was possible at the time. Because he was a senior officer, wasn't he?
He was a captain. Captain. He was then reported missing.
We never heard anything more about him, assuming that he was killed back then
I think it was in '42. And now her name was Renate Eitel.
And a woman worked with her as a sister who was married to a high-ranking National Socialist
which my aunt didn't know at the time. Do you know the names of the sons there?
No, no, unfortunately I don't know.
And she obviously applied for my aunt to be made an honorary Aryan without my aunt's knowledge.
Without, uh, your aunt's child, yes?
Yes, that automatically means the child too, because if she's an honorary Aryan
then the child is too.
And was, um, she pregnant then or had you already had the child?
The child had already been born and, uh, a few weeks later to her great surprise
my aunt received a certificate in which she was named an honorary Aryan.
Uh, about eight days later she was summoned to the Gestapo because she had been denounced.
She was in trouble from an institute
I think it was a housing distribution office or something like that. Mhm.
Uh, she called these people a corrupt society.
And that's why she was summoned to the Gestapo
but she took this certificate of honor with her as a precaution. Mhm.
When she was in the office and was questioned
she showed this honorary officer's certificate
whereupon the Gestapo officer showed her a certificate stating that she had been sent to a concentration camp and then tore it up.
So this certificate practically saved her life.
And when you found out about this Aryanization, what did you think about it?
I was speechless. I didn't even think it was possible that such a thing existed.
But I thought, good for her. You did - it's a shame we don't have it.
Did you try to get that too? Because that was the sister. Yes. Yours-- Yes.
My mother.
My mother obviously, obviously hadn't done anything, so we were left in the same state as before.
But did that give you a bit of hope or not? No.
Did you think that was a one-off, or? We suspected that it must be very rare.
Mmm. We'd never heard of it before and also, er
only found out later in the post-war period that there were exceptional cases.
Mhm.
For example, when I was a prisoner of war, I heard that Field Marshal Milch was a half-breed.
But that was the first case I, uh, heard about, apart from my own aunt. Hm.
Back to her military service. Yes.
When you were given a Wehrmacht uniform and you used it. Yes.
What did you think? I didn't have any particular thoughts.
I was aware that I was one of millions of others. I, uh- Did that help you?
Consciously, I mean. It was a bit of a protection. Mhm.
Uh, a protection, uh, not, uh, being able to be arrested so easily
since I now represent the state myself in uniform.
That's how I felt at the time. Mhm. Was that really the case? Mm.
And was your brother in the same company? No, no.
I was in the pioneers, armored engineers. He joined the artillery.
And was his experience like your experience? Was he, uh...
I suppose more or less, yes. Mmm.
Everyone feels differently, of course, but roughly the same.
For example, when there were fights at school
because someone thought he had to beat me up if possible.
Then he always came to my aid, right. And, uh, so we had a sense of cohesion.
Mhm. And what did your comrades say they were fighting for?
What did they fight for, yes? What reason did you give for that?
Uh, the comrades said very little. That was the official propaganda
which claimed that they were defending Greater Germany against this and that.
Uh, that, uh, I actually, as soon as I became more aware, uh
was able to think for myself in puberty, it was clear to me that that was, uh
propaganda, exaggeration and nonsense.
Uh, I was actually already aware during the French campaign
when they occupied Belgium and Holland, later Norway, uh
and then later other countries, that they hadn't done anything to us.
Why do you-- why do you do that? Or even the declaration of war on America.
What chance do we have against that?
Of course I didn't tell anyone that, but I was already aware of how things were going.
And did your comrades feel like fighting? Some of them, yes. Hm.
And did you, yes, as a child, let's say, did you hope that Germany would win the war?
When I was young, at the beginning of the war, still more of a child, not yet an adolescent.
Back then, yes. But I mean in the military. No, no. For God's sake, no.
There is-- I also remember that once an officer, uh, who probably belonged to a propaganda unit.
He gave lectures like that and the company was seconded and he spoke very suggestively and also talked about the final victory and the secret weapons and all that and then asked them how comradely they were.
Now everyone should say honestly whether they believe that this victory is not...
That this war could no longer be won. And not a single person came forward.
But I still remember feeling guilty because I didn't believe it and was too cowardly to say it.
That's how I thought at the time. Today I'm glad it was like that. Hm. Yes.
Please. Didn't you once say that you were happy when the flak hit? Yes.
That's right. Right? We were deployed as air force helpers. I was in a...
First in a ten-point-five-centimeter battery, later in an eight-point-eight-centimeter battery.
And there were the, um, American or English squadrons, when they moved over us and then...
The planes were shot at. We also saw planes crash several times.
And I saw that, uh, together with my comrades, as a success.
And I was-- Because I also saw that, uh, these airplane attacks, uh
caused a lot of damage in Karlsruhe and other cities
and usually not to military objects, but to civilian buildings.
And how many planes did you shoot down? Or rather, the battery I was in.
Uh, officially, I think we were credited with two or three kills at the time.
But you know, I was able to observe that at the time. Uh
it depended a lot on which company commander was able to present the matter to the regimental commander as if it had been his battery.
As a rule
there were always several batteries firing afterwards and it was never possible to determine exactly what caused the plane to crash.
I was also lucky enough not to be at the cannon myself, but in the so-called defense tower.
This was a section that was only deployed if the optical measuring device failed and the radio measuring device failed or vice versa.
Then we had to pass on certain numbers and I never had to do that
so I personally, uh, wasn't directly involved in the killing of another person.
Not even later in the military. And today that's a...
I'm very glad about that today.
Was your father, uh, your brother, was he in combat? For one, uh, two days.
And what did he say about it?
Uh, that they were heavily shot at, that comrades fell next to them.
I don't know myself whether he fired too.
In any case, he was then taken prisoner. He was in the West, yes?
He was captured near Heilbronn and I was captured in Ulm.
Okay, so with the Americans. Yes.
When did you find out about, uh, the Holocaust?
I found out about concentration camps relatively early on.
Uh, around 1942 or '43, I heard other people tell me, uh
that SS people had come on vacation who were in a very bad way and who had said that the concentration camps they were in were horrible.
But they weren't allowed to say anything because then they themselves might be
uh, sentenced to death.
But it was so horrible that you couldn't say anything about it.
And that's when I began to realize that the Jews, who everyone knew would one day be gone.
And not just the emigrants, we knew that they had left
but that the others who had been sent to camps were not only doing very badly
but it seemed likely to me at the time that these people had also been killed.
I didn't know any more details, but I assume that if I
as a fourteen-year-old or fifteen-year-old, heard that at the time
then other people must have heard it too.
So if they kept saying later: "Yes, I have no idea." These people
they repressed it or they don't admit it.
And, uh, also the threats with concentration camps.
You didn't hear the name Auschwitz, but Dachau, for example
was a well-known concentration camp whose name was heard more often.
And, uh, in captivity... After the first few weeks
after I came from the collection camp to a labor camp, that's when, uh
we prisoners of war also became known.
And then I was also astonished that it had been carried out on such a huge scale
that millions of people had been killed, and, uh
at that time more than half of my German comrades dismissed it as American propaganda and said: "That can't be true." Hm.
And after the war, did you ever feel guilty about what you did at the, at the flat, right?
No, uh, not that. I, uh, I didn't see the big picture back then.
I wasn't ashamed of it. I was ashamed of something else, though.
I wasn't just in an anti-aircraft battery, but later also in the Stab regiment
and they also had Russian prisoners of war as auxiliaries. Mhm.
And one of these Russian auxiliaries once offered me a job in arts and crafts if I could give him bread in return.
And I didn't do it and I'm still ashamed of that today.
And during that time, did you lose any Jewish relatives in the Holocaust? No.
Hm. And with your aunt- Hai--, you knew that this
this Aryanization was her salvation from the concentration camp man? Yes.
The Gestapo. Yes. Were you afraid for yourself that you would also be deported?
Uh, I was afraid that something might happen to me, but I didn't realize how it might happen.
Mhm. And about those Russians.
Why didn't you feel more, yes, compassion for him?
Were you afraid to help him, were you? A little, yes. For what?
Was it forbidden? Yes. Forbidden to do that? Yes, that was forbidden. Hm.
And how did he react when you said, "No." He withdrew. He had no other choice.
Hmm. And why did this event, why did it, uh, make such a deep impression on you?
Because I realized that the situation itself, uh, made me react inhumanely. Hm.
Is it your fault or is it the society you grew up in, uh.
Especially with this Nazi propaganda, is that to blame?
I don't just want to blame others. It's always yourself as well.
Of course they were the cause, but I mean, I could have reacted differently.
Mmm.
Did your mother find it strange that you and your brother had to serve in the German Wehrmacht as so-called half-breeds?
Yes. Hm. And did you talk to your mother about it? I can't remember.
What good would it have done? Mhm.
It would have, it would have turned out the way it was supposed to.
We would have had to report to the military, we would have gone. Mhm.
And your mother, were you afraid of being deported? I think so, yes.
She hoped that she would be spared that
because my father was severely war-damaged from the First World War
fifty percent, he was hard of hearing.
And it could be that, uh, that the reason was that nothing happened to her.
Uh, I suspect that if that had gone on any longer
all the half-Jews might have been deported as well.
She was lucky that nothing happened to her. Hm.
From all your experiences back then, what have you learned for your life?
Uh, to be tolerant even towards minorities, for example.
Whether it's the Turks today or someone else tomorrow.
Uh, it's, uh, self-evident to me that, uh
no one is inferior to anyone else because of, uh
their origin or religion or anything else. That's completely nonsensical.
Uh-huh. Doctor, thank you. Sir, can you say your name? What is your name?
For my documentation. Heinz Schindler. And where and when were you born?
02.06.13. Mhm. And where?
And when you were young, did you know that you were of Jewish descent?
From the beginning, yes. Hm. Were you brought up in Jewish customs, or? No. Hm.
Because my Jewish father left the Jewish community in Berlin out of political conviction.
Did he give a reason for that? A what? Give a reason for it?
He was a convinced socialist and dissident, as they call it.
Although he came from an orthodox household.
And, uh, did he have trouble with his parents because he married a non-Jewish woman?
Yes. Hm. Yes, very much so. Hm. But he didn't care. Hm. And on the other hand
your mother's parents had difficulties because they- My mother had no, uh
parents who had died very young. My mother grew up with so-called step-parents.
There were no problems at all.
What's more, my mother only met my father when she had long, uh, passed away.
How old was my mother? Uhhh, about twenty-six years old.
So, she was in charge of herself. She wasn't responsible to anyone. Hmmm.
So, how were you brought up in religion? Uhhh, as a dissident. Dissident, yes.
Without any religious affiliation. Hmmm.
The fact that it was different afterwards was a tactical technical move, nothing more.
Hmmm. And did you have contact with your Jewish grandparents?
Yes, not grandparents, but grandmother. Hmmm. Uh, three aunts, two uncles. Hmmm.
And did you go to the synagogue a lot?
But yes, I even sang on the Jewish holidays of Shom Kippur and Rosh Ha-Shanah.
In a liberal synagogue. Sure- Hmmm.
-had to be liberal, because the Orthodox didn't sing in the choir. Hmmm.
And do you still remember your prayers or your songs? But yes. Oh.
Can you, uh, repeat that?
Yes, let's start with Ma Tow or, uh, all, uh Asehle man schmecho.
Anything like that. Do you do that these days? No. (laughs) So, yes.
Can you describe your childhood, uh, to the students?
It was a very normal childhood. Hmmm.
Did you have any difficulties because of your- Not at all.
That didn't exist in my time. Ha. So when the Nazis came to power - yes.
-Did you talk to your parents about what we should do, maybe go abroad, or?
Not at all. That wasn't an issue at all. Hmm.
So, what did you think when Hitler came to power? Yes.
(takes a deep breath) Uh, that was an inevitable fate. Hmm.
Determined by many factors that have long since become common knowledge.
Unemployment, the shaky democracy
the right-wing circles from the old officers around Ludendorff, Hohenberg
Stahlhelm.
That was one side that was constantly working against the Weimar Republic in-- And on the other side
of course, was communism, wasn't it? In 1925, for example, when Ebert died
a new Reich President had to be elected and the entire right-wing coalition
from the German Nationals at the top down to the Center, uh, put up Hindenburg.
And the Social Democrats had their own candidate.
And the worst thing in my view was that the Communists also had their own candidate.
So that means, together- Hmhm.
-Social Democrats and Communists could have easily got their candidate through.
But the fact that the Communists always insisted on representing their own, uh
interests, that was completely wrong and apolitical.
In other words, from my point of view
the Communists were largely to blame for the National Socialists coming to power in 1933.
The fact that they had to pay for it all afterwards is another matter. Hmhm.
Yes, and that's how I grew up and when I wasn't quite so affected by it, I became seriously ill.
In other words, during the transition period I was in hospital with severe kidney poisoning.
And when that had subsided, as I was a musician, I went back to making music on a freelance basis.
Then came the first big blow: I was no longer allowed to pursue my profession as a musician because the so-called Reichsmusikkammer didn't accept me and my brother.
Do you know the encyclopedia Jews in Music? Aha, you see. But I have it.
That means I'm in an encyclopaedia during my lifetime.
Although not very edifying
because this encyclopaedia was only intended for the official use of the NSDAP.
In other words, all the so-called administrators
everyone who had anything to do with music in the so-called Third Reich
had this encyclopaedia on their desk.
And it listed all those who were either Jewish.
Jewish by blood, not the quarter-Jews, they weren't in there.
But composers like Mendelssohn Bartholdy, like Gustav Mahler
conductors like Blech, Bruno Walter Klemperer were all in there.
And I have the honor of being in it too.
I'm proud of that, even though it was directed against me at the time.
So that means that nobody hired me because I was in that dictionary. Yes.
Shall we show him? What's your brother's name?
My brother is deceased, but he's also in the dictionary. Hm. What's his name?
Erwin. Erwin.
That's the one who was in that squad with Wolfgang Behrend, Günter Lebrandt
Werner Gransch, Bosshardt, who weren't in the Wehrmacht
they were in the so-called UT, weren't they? That was a forced labor formation.
And my brother was there. I myself served as the lowest rank in the Wehrmacht.
As you can see, that's the success. You can easily get this book in anyone.
What did you say? Which archive are you with? The Federal Archives. Of course.
Do you want to make a note of that? Yes, afterward. Oh, I told you.
Give me that, child. Here you are. This is the lexicon of Jews in music.
Von Stengel crossed out the court.
Those were the two rascals who compiled it with a list of titles of Jewish works on behalf of the Reichsleitung der NSDAP on the basis of official party-approved documents
edited by Dr.
Theo Stengel, consultant at the Reichsmusikkammer in conjunction with Dr. habil.
Herbert Gerig
Head of the Main Office for Music at the Führer's Commissioner for the Supervision of the NSDAP's entire intellectual and ideological training and education.
The worst thing is that these two thugs. After 1945.
in the judicial authority of Lower Saxony. One was a public prosecutor.
I don't know what the other one did.
I once thought I'd go there and murder them or something.
But it wouldn't have been any use.
So they still had well-paid jobs in the so-called republic after 1945.
And now, of course, I'm drawing a parallel with today's Federal Republic.
Politically, it stinks everywhere here.
You have the recent events in the Bundeswehr, the right-wing extremists, the anti-Semites.
That's how it started in the Weimar Republic.
And today we're at that point again. So. What else do you want to know?
So, in 1935, please? In 1935, when the Nuremberg Laws came out. But before that.
I was already at these documents before that. Before 35. That's the nastiness.
But when you were suddenly a so-called half-Jew, in 35, with these new laws
what did you think about it? What was I supposed to think?
I was glad that they didn't pick me up.
And I earned my living doing very menial work in a factory as an unskilled laborer and was glad that they didn't get me.
That worked. You said you were with the Schmechel brother. The...
They were three brothers.
And I worked in a factory until I was nineteen thirty-nine
until the beginning of the Second World War, which produced so-called pills
machines, I don't know, for the whole, uh, what do you call it, Mona?
A pharmacy or- Yes, yes. Well, they make pills, medicines.
I was employed there as a small worker.
And the moment the war started, the authorized signatory
who was actually quite sympathetic to me, called me in and said: "Mr.
Schindler, we have to part company with you, because we're a military company from now on.
We all have to be sworn in and you can't be sworn in." Yes. Then, uh
since there was a shortage of work because so many people had been drafted
I ended up in a machine factory in Moabit.
Since I was already familiar with accounting, payroll accounting and, and, and
and, worker cards and, and, and, um
I got a position there as a post-calculator, as it was called.
And there was one of my, how should I put it, colleagues
he was quite young at the time, standing at the lathe. That was Horst Schmechel.
I've known him since 1940, Horst. He lives in Dortmund. Did you ever visit him?
Mhm. Yes. You were in Dortmund then too? Yes, he was.
Didn't he tell you about me? No. A little bit. Please?
He said a bit-- He said that, uh, you met someone else back then. Yes.
But I was much older than him. He was still an apprentice back then.
(bell ringing) In 1936, I was officially sent to the, uh, Wehrmacht examination
that is, a soldier's examination. I don't know what that shit is called.
Mustering. Mustering, right.
Yes, these things, uh, don't let me articulate properly
because then I always get the coffee up when I think about this crap. Mmm.
So I was drafted in '36 and my kidney disease from 1934 still had an effect.
You know, you have to urinate and, and, and.
And so I still had a very high protein content and was written up as unfit.
Now I have to proceed in the same way.
Uh, nineteen forty-one, end of nineteen forty-one.
I lived in Berlin in Wedding and now comes something that's not so obvious or anything.
When I say, "Yes, why?" A Nazi, a teacher, lived above me and he had a Polish maid.
And he took this oaf of a girl and my mother suffered because of it.
And I listened to it for quite a while and at least I didn't want my mother to...
I don't know anymore. I'm a bit choleric, maybe.
I went up there, banged on the door and made a mess of them, as we say in Germany.
So I shouted, yes, and also insulted them, telling them to leave my mother alone.
She complained to her employer, Mr.
Flöter, the teacher, and he reported me to the police.
He was an old Nazi and you know these organizations, local groups and so on.
And I was summoned there for questioning. That was very interesting.
Well, when you live in an area for decades, especially in a working-class area
which was Wedding, you were known. That's quite clear.
Everyone knew everyone in the nearby houses.
And this conversation between the so-called local group leader and Mr.
Flöter on the one hand and me sitting on the other as a defendant.
No, I wasn't sitting, I had to stand.
And then, uh, the local group leader shouted at me what I was thinking
I was born in Berlin in the third generation.
I was only, uh, a guest in Germany, how could I come to insult this Polish servant girl.
And he will make sure that I get into the concentration camp.
And then I heard, I'll never forget: "Comrade, Party comrade Flöter
leave me alone with the man now." I thought I might get beaten or whatever.
And this teacher was outside and I just said that everyone there knew everyone in the
yes, in the nearest houses. That means I grew up there, mhm.
And then the local group leader changed his tone and said to me: "Heinz
how can you do something like that?
I've known you for so long, you know me." Local group leader of the NSDAP.
Well, I have to-- "He insists that you go to a concentration camp." "Yes
" I say, "I can, but I can only try one thing.
Uh, write to the Führer's office and tell them that you've never been noticed
that you..." And, and, and, "I'll write a good report for you.
Maybe you can be accepted into the Wehrmacht. But not into the regular Wehrmacht
but into a probationary battalion." So I was first examined again on the basis of this letter and was healthy.
My kidney disease was over. A few months later, in April, I got my call-up.
Uh, with a facsimile letter signed by the so-called Führer, Adolf Hitler, that criminal.
He never signed it, of course
because it said that the conscription of Jewish half-breeds of the first or second degree into the Wehrmacht could only be carried out with the personal exception of the Führer.
All nonsense. That was signed by the, the, the, uh, what's his name?
That Bormann signed it, the Hitler-Bemuh-- nonsense.
So I was drafted and five days later, my mother told me
two SS men stood outside our apartment door and wanted to pick me up to go to the concentration camp.
And I had now escaped from the clutches of the SS.
I couldn't-- they couldn't lick my ass anymore.
And then I had a really interesting time in a probation battalion.
But if I told you all that, I'd be sitting here until tomorrow morning.
There you go. No, no, that's no use at all.
Uh, my wingman, he was one-eighty tall in our little bunch, he was a, uh
former lieutenant general from the First World War, demoted.
Had the Pour le mérite.
Then they were all, uh, accounting sergeants, um, and whatever the guys were called.
And they had embezzled whole wagons of chocolate and alcohol, they were demoted.
One, uh, first lieutenant
who was in the intelligence-- some intelligence department
was demoted because he had committed a serious offense against a twelve-year-old Russian girl.
So that happened too. Good.
Uh, I was sent to the Demyansk cauldron, that was on Lake Ilmen
in the northern part of Russia, after my basic training and whatnot.
Well, and that's where my arm blew up in my face on February 19, '43. (I was.
I had-- oh, by the way, interesting: on the Wehrmacht blouse, people always get it all mixed up.
Probationary battalion and punishment battalion.
The people from the punishment battalion had no insignia at all and nothing.
We in the probation battalion even wore this swastika, this one, on our Wehrmacht uniform.
But as I said, I was just a rifleman's ass, as they called it in Germany.
And on February 19, '43, I was wounded.
Well, then the usual route through the many military hospitals and, and, and.
I came to Berlin in October '43.
Now I told you that I, my brother too, sang in a liberal synagogue during the holidays.
I had or have a very good voice, my brother too.
And of course I was very interesting as a tenor for various professional choirs in 1943.
And so there was a radio choir in Berlin and the conductor, a salami
was delighted that he now had a tenor again because most of them had been drafted.
The joy lasted less than four weeks.
Then I had to go down to the so-called personnel department.
And there sat a Sturmbannführer. Didn't you remember his name?
Sturmbannführer of the SS. "Tell me, what are you doing here?" Söhnchen.
Me: "Yes, son, I'm in the choir with Mr.
Lamy." Literally now: "Even if you are severely war-damaged
you are and will remain a Jewish half-breed and now you are coming to the house." Hmmm
hmmm. Then I swore to myself: "When these thugs are gone
I'll be the first one (tapping my fingers on the table) to go into the Funkhaus." That's how it was.
And if you want to know from me
I've already said it before: I'm very depressed about the development in the Federal Republic.
Just think of Mr. Globke.
But most of my so-called comrades no longer concern themselves with these things.
They don't even know anything about it anymore. Think of Gehlen.
Are they all terms? Yes, these thugs? And who sponsored them? Mr. Adenauer.
Well, let's leave it. I'm just getting upset, it's no use.
So now you know a lot about me. Sören zu Militär was in your company. Yes.
Were there any other men who were Jewish-- No, no.
They were all just demoted, uh, officers. And did you see your permit?
The authorization on you? That the Führer signed? Mhm.
Yes, yes, I had it, but I no longer have it. Hmm.
What did you think about it at the time? What should I have thought?
I thought: "Thank God I'm not going to a concentration camp." Mhm. That's clear.
And what was the camaraderie like? Bad. Very bad. Hmm. Very bad.
I can tell you two incidents.
Im-- I was in the front line in the trenches in a positional war, so not in combat, uh...
Well, we were in a trench war, in the trenches.
And, uh, between us and the Russian front line was maybe na-- at most, but at most a kilometer.
There were trenches over there too.
And between the trenches were Spanish horsemen.
You know what a Spanish horseman is? You know that. Uh-huh. Mm.
And, uh, there was a first lieutenant
that's the one who went on the Russian twelve-year-old girl ride
so I can tell him, he stared her dead. Yes.
And it was a miracle that he was brought to justice at all
because he was decorated with the German Cross in gold and everything.
But as I said, he was demoted.
And we had a very nice (scoffs)-what do you mean nice? Nonsense.
Russian propaganda with loudspeakers. It was like that everywhere.
They knew very well that we were a Berlin, uh, company, uh, of, uh-- you see
I'm at a loss for words-- of demoted men. Mhm.
And said: "We know you're from Berlin. Come over here to us." Literally.
"There are horny women and white beds waiting for you here." I've never forgotten that.
"There are horny women and white beds waiting for you here." My ass.
Uh, so quite a few people did try to, uh, cross over, but not from my company.
There were only two cases, I'll tell you about them briefly.
For me it was out of the question, because if I had tried to cross over
my mother and my brother would have been arrested immediately.
My brother was still living in Berlin. He was.
So that was out of the question for me.
(clears throat) There was a first lieutenant, he was a first lieutenant in an intelligence unit.
And, uh, he disappeared one day.
Nobody, uh, gave it any thought, because I told you, the so-called comradeship was shit.
It didn't exist at all. Everyone lived for themselves and...
I can prove that later with an example. So one day this lieutenant left.
This highly decorated first lieutenant, who had been demoted, suddenly disappeared.
He reappeared three days later.
He had somehow overcome the Spanish horsemen, got to the Russian line and
as a naturally trained intelligence officer, tapped the telephone line to the
er, battalion, to the Russian battalion.
So he had prepared himself for this and after three days he arrives with us and has the line in tow so that our offices can listen in on all the communications with the Russians.
(clears throat) The man was immediately recalled to his old rank.
So he immediately became a first lieutenant again
was allowed to wear all his medals and then we lost sight of him.
That didn't let a non-commissioned officer rest.
He also wanted to become a non-commissioned officer again or whatever.
And he made an attempt to do something over there. Probably didn't get very far.
I don't even know if he got past the wire ban.
And then we heard him screaming day and night.
He'd been shot by the Russians and must have been-- And we gathered that from his...
He screamed for a long time. He must have been shot in the stomach.
And the camaraderie among us was so great that no one even cared about the guy.
We thought: "Oh well, if he does that, it's his own business." Then he bled to death.
We didn't give a damn. Yes? That's how hard it was there.
And that's how good the camaraderie was. And when you became a soldier. Me?
What did you think about that?
Did you think: "That's funny that I was a-" I told you earlier
I told you earlier, I was glad I didn't have to go to a concentration camp.
Maybe I'm that cowardly, I don't know.
Or should I have gone to the concentration camp with my head held high?
Is that a question for me? Yes.
Yes, I, yes, the idea, you know, (chuckle) I don't believe that.
But with your mother, did you talk to your mother and brother about what you were doing - when?
Before they got that authorization, what you should do to protect the family.
I always did what I wanted. I never asked anyone.
And I had such a good relationship with my mother, who was naturally afraid for me.
Because of the SS. And where was your Jewish father during this time?
He was buried in 1934, no, '36. 1936 in Bahia in the English cemetery.
He had an assignment, because he spoke perfect Spanish and Portuguese
to create a Jewish refuge for Jewish emigrants, for Jewish refugees
in a jungle area. Under the most difficult conditions.
My father only lived there for a few days and, er, was probably bitten by an insect.
He had to be taken to Bahia by motorboat on some river.
He was already dead by then and was buried there in the English cemetery.
A Polish fellow believer accompanied my father on the motorboat and you know that it is a duty of honor for a Jewish person to help a dead fellow believer
to wash him, to read him the prayers for the dead and to say them.
Even though my father was a so-called dissident. There's no such thing.
A Jew remains a Jew. And he was always happy when he heard us singing. Sure.
Asselmann Schimero or Matau or and, and, and.
Yes, and now you know all about me. Do you feel Jewish yourself? Uh, no.
I don't have the upbringing for that.
I, it was like this, my brother is three years older and was born before marriage.
And then my Jewish father married my Protestant mother.
And then I was born in wedlock.
And then my father's orthodox Jewish mother tried to have my grandson circumcised.
And my mother fought tooth and nail against it.
And then, of course, there was the divide.
My grandmother never forgave my mother for that. They're Texans.
My orthodox Jewish grandmother was born in an Indian tent in the USA.
My grandfather came from Galicia or whatever.
Emigrated to America because of the pogroms, got himself a little old horse, a, what do you call it?
Uh. Uh. A wagon like that. Yes, a covered wagon. Yes, a covered wagon. Yes. Mhm.
Packed the covered wagon full of pots, with, uh, anything that might be knives
forks, uh, something that was interesting for Indians back then.
And, uh, on the Indian reservation, my great-grandmother went into labor.
And they brought her into a tent.
And the Indian women were so great at that sort of thing, the indigenous people.
A birth was a small thing. And they helped my grandmother, er, into life.
And my grandmother had, that's why I'm telling you this, of course she was a US citizen.
She was born in the USA.
And in that respect she was untouchable for the Nazis in Berlin and had the flag of the USA on her front door and stamped underneath: uh
extraterritorial territory of the USA.
That meant that the SS or SA were not allowed to enter the apartment.
My grandmother died, I think at nineteen forty.
The next day, the SS came and picked up my two aunts, who were still living with my mother.
What were your aunts' names? Auntie, well Schindler, of course.
She was unmarried. One aunt was sent to Riga, had to dig her own grave
was shot and the other aunt was sent to Theresienstadt and died there.
I deliberately say "perished". I don't say "died".
I am, if you like, full of hatred for the whole baggage.
Uh, and therefore also, I tell you, for the masses of the German people.
Because look at the pictures of them waving and cheering for the rag.
And my fear is that perhaps not to the same extent
but that we have now reached a point again where anti-Semitism, racism, er
is raising its cheeky head.
And to an extent that we would never have believed in nineteen forty-five.
It's appalling. And, uh, I deal with these things a lot.
I'm thinking of the harrowing speech by Otto Wels. You're not familiar with it.
Otto Wels was the leader of the Social Democrats' parliamentary group in the Reichstag
where the Communists had already been kicked out after this engineered Reichstag fire by Göring.
And then the Nazis submitted their so-called authorization motion
which of course put all the power in the hands of these thugs.
And everyone agreed. Are you familiar with Theodor Heuss?
You see, Theodor Heuss also agreed.
Back then as a member of parliament from the Center, uh, uh
or as a Democrat from the Democratic Party. In any case, he voted with us.
The only one who dared to stand up against it said in a, of course very moderate
shocking speech that he and his parliamentary group could not agree to this Enabling Act
this Enabling Act. That speech was appalling.
I don't know what happened to Otto Wels. During your military service.
After you were wounded - yes. Did you continue to serve in the German Wehrmacht?
No. You were discharged? I was discharged, yes.
And did you have a- I told you that. Then I sang in the choir.
So I was discharged. But not in the Wehrmacht choir? No, in the radio choir.
Berlin radio. And then this SS-Sturmbannführer kicked me out.
Did you get special permission because of your serious injury? No. (laughs) Why?
I'm just telling you. Mhm.
The Sturmbannführer said that even if I was severely wounded in the war
even if you were severely, severely wounded in the war
you would remain a Jewish person. Make sure you get out.
But what did the Wehrmacht say? Nothing at all. What should they say?
The Wehrmacht isn't interested at all.
What kind of constitution do you have in mind under "Wehrmacht"?
I didn't even exist for them. Mhm.
Were you allowed to get medals in your company? Honors? Yes.
I was automatically entitled to the silver medal for the wounded and I should have been promoted to private.
Neither happened. The Wehrmacht gave you a reason why? Yes.
It was swept under the table, swept under the carpet.
You can't blame me for being so clear here. No, please.
It always makes my head spin when I think about it. Hm Zuavang is enough.
How are you wounded? What happened? Why don't you talk here?
Yes, but what happened in Russia? In Russia. It was a so-called Ratsch. Boom.
I can't tell myself that.
It's an artillery shell that creaks and scatters at about that height.
And that's how my arm was shot through. And did your comrades help you?
Immediately, yes. Immediately. Oh, I wasn't with the company then.
I was in a medical tent because of lice.
Yes, yes, no, they helped me straight away.
So, you joined a normal company later, with this medic. When later?
After you were wounded? No, you said before I was wounded.
That's when I was relieved of those horrible points on the rifle slope
because I'd had a solitary attack.
And in the army, did your comrades "feel like fighting? What did they have?
A desire to fight. Oh, where from? So what did your comrades fight for?
Well, their lives, because they wanted to.
They weren't interested in what was over there or anywhere else.
They were just fighting for survival.
And did the people under someone else talk about Hitler to the government?
Oh dear, where? No. How were we supposed to talk politics over there?
That would have been completely wrong.
They had to see everyone else as a traitor.
Did you have to swear an oath to Hitler in this preservation battalion? No.
No, I wasn't sworn in. I don't think so. I can't say that for sure now.
I don't think I was sworn in. I don't think so. Or I do.
I know, I can't answer that for you.
But if I had been asked, I would have done so. Of course I would have.
I'm not a hero. Who did you actually hope, apart from the teacher, I think
would get permission to stay in the German Wehrmacht?
That local group leader, I told him just now. And his whole name?
Is he running around? I can't remember his name. No, I don't remember.
But had other people written letters for you? Recommendation letters?
No, no, no, nothing. Did you send photos there? What? Photos of you?
No, not really. So how long did it take you to talk to this leader?
To the group leader, yes. Until you got the authorization. How many weeks?
Four months. Four months. What was your hope for the future during that time?
Did you think that if I didn't have the opportunity, I would leave?
Or did you think I could have a life in Germany?
I just have to survive through this war.
If I hadn't lost this arm, I would have been the first to emigrate to Israel.
I would have emigrated to Israel immediately. So why didn't you do that?
What did I want? With one arm, what was I supposed to do?
They only needed people who could work well in the kibbutz, who could get stuck in.
That's not even a question. Do you feel a strong connection with Israel?
A first cousin was an airplane observer during the Six-Day War and one of my father's brothers
my uncle, who had just come over in 1936, lived in the Dominican Republic
then in Argentina and visited his nephew in Israel
this military airplane observer. And he refused to talk to his uncle in German.
I think that's all right. I think that's very right. Yes.
Have you been to Israel? No, never before.
I have no intention of going there either. That's not a contradiction at all.
I'm also very, very critical of that. Everything that's happening in Israel.
Have they not learned from the 6 million gassed?
I couldn't have foreseen that at the time.
In 1945, who would have believed that this Risches, this Netanyahu
the murdered rabbi, would go off? It's going to blow up. I'm telling you. Why?
After the war, you tried to live in another country, (crosstalk 00:00:09) except Germany.
No, but not as a gravity-damaged person. You must realize that.
Which country is interested in taking in a gravity-damaged person?
Have you tried? But you didn't, you didn't, uh, like living in Germany.
Did you after the Adenauer and Globka, uh, event.
Did you think, maybe, I should go away from this country? No, no.
It didn't go that far. I saw it with contempt. I saw it with disdain
but nobody could take away my relationship to German culture
or above all to German music.
Nobody has taken that away from me and still hasn't.
I still deal with my god, if you like. That is Gustav Mahler.
I was already familiar with Gustav Mahler's symphonies when Gustav Mahler wasn't even a household name.
Today you hear, ahem, that's en vogue.
I had my first encounter with Gustav Mahler in 1930, with the, uh
first symphony, with the Titan, when I was at college. Mmm.
So, now you know so much about me. And what did you play? I was a clarinettist.
And, uh, yes, I'd like to go back to your military service, when you were in Russia.
Yes. What kind of weapons did you have?
Wa-weapon course or position it's called.
(crosstalk 00:01:42) Was, were you a, were (crosstalk 00:01:43) you a little infantryman, right?
No, I, uh, had to be there in the, at the machine gun, uh-- So
but now I'll tell you another story about the comradeship and that's scythe.
I was on duty, uh, New Year's Eve 1942 at night, 1942 to '43.
And we were relieved every two hours.
Machine gun duty, then we went back and had, we had, uh
two big shell funnels with, uh, blankets laid out.
That was our rest point and so on.
And I had, uh, duty for two hours in the trench from, what we say today, twenty-two o'clock.
Back then we said ten o'clock to midnight
so exactly until (claps hands) the new year or the end of the year.
And I waited for my replacement. It didn't come. Didn't come.
I stood there for four hours until two o'clock in the morning and then finally a replacement came.
Then I went to the back, what was at the back.
There was half a bottle of champagne and chocolate for everyone.
They stole everything from me. That was the camaraderie.
When did you find out about the Holocaust? When? Mhm.
I told you what happened to my aunts. Yes. What happened to my uncles.
My God, I have to go again... My father went to Brazil. Uh-huh.
My uncles-- Well, do they still have enough? Yes? Nothing left.
(crosstalk 00:04:03) Uh, one uncle went to Shanghai. Mhm.
The other one went to the Dominican Republic first.
My father, as I said, went to Brazil. Mhm. Of course I knew all that. Hm.
Of course.
Why didn't you tell me- (crosstalk 00:04:23) The horrific events in Galicia.
What they did to the Jewish people. Did you see that as a soldier?
No, when I was there-- I wasn't in a section, uh, but I was in the jungle, if you like.
We were practically in the jungle, in the so-called Demyansk cauldron. Mhm.
Uh, that's on Lake Ilmen. The starting point was Stalaja Russa.
There were no Jews there, there weren't any. We were practically in the forest.
Mhm.
Did any of your comrades know that she was a so-called (crosstalk 00:05:02) half-Jew?
No, nope. I was also demoted. Nothing more. Mhm.
Were you afraid that someone would find out about it?
Oh, they wouldn't have been interested. Hmm. Really-really?
Did, did you, when you, uh... Did you have a vacation? A what?
When you were in the German army. Did you have a, a leave? Were you on leave?
Yes. Never? No. Not one day while I was a soldier. Yes.
I was on leave after every military hospital. Hm.
And do you have other people in your family that you lost
apart from these two aunts in the Holocaust? From the Jewish side? Mhm. No.
So it was just the two aunts who stupidly stayed in Germany because they thought they were protected by their mother's
uh, US citizenship. Mhm. Yes, that ended the day my grandmother closed her eyes.
The next day, the SS came and picked up my two aunts.
The other siblings all went and came abroad, all of them.
And what do you think would have happened if Germany had won the war?
What would have happened to you? We all don't know.
We can only theorize about that.
But we probably would have had to, uh, get off the sidewalk and, uh
maybe we would have been sent to labor camps or whatever. Hm.
And in Russia, did you see the Russians? Of course I did. (laughs) Hm.
Was it difficult, uh, to shoot at other people? Oh, like where. Oh.
We didn't, we didn't do it at all. I didn't fire a single shot in the whole war.
But you were a machine gunner, yes? Yes. I didn't need to be.
So, how did you - that, I would only have set it in motion if they had launched an assault.
But they were just as happy in the trenches as we were. Hm.
And what was your worst memory as a soldier in Russia? Pff. Worst memory? Mhm.
Jo. That we couldn't clear out. Hm. You realize I'm getting ironic now.
That's obvious. And you know what clearing is. There you go.
And from all your experiences, what have you learned for your life?
From back then? I have to tell you
I told you earlier: I was already very independent as a boy and I didn't need to learn more.
I just observed it all.
I saw myself like an outsider and I still see myself today.
I am happy that I have two wives - my first wife died - that I have this angel here.
But we both limit ourselves.
We live very secluded lives and I hope for a very, very long time. And, uh
but you've probably gathered from a lot of this that I'm still involved in, uh
politics, in the events of the day, but again
just like an outsider watching a movie go by.
Of course I take a stand for myself. Mmm.
And you and I have always agreed on everything, including politics.
We don't need anyone. We watch it, take a stand. Off.
I don't know if you can see what's there. Do you know that? Say it again?
The song you said on Yom Kippur. That was too long ago. Yes. So...
But can you, uh, say that, uh, prayer for, uh, again, what you sang a little bit?
That was nice. Well, at the beginning? Mhm. (sings) Lehu adanoj elohenu.
(sings) Jischnah-- uh, uh, uh.
Jischnaseh, lehu alehu, jischnas, jischnah, chis, ah, they're all gone.
(sings) Lehu adanaj elohim. That's how we started the New Year, I think.
That was the beginning of- Rosh Hashana? Of the N-- Yes, Rosh Hashana.
(sings) Lehu adanaj elohenu. But that's all I know about it now. And the Shma?
Do you still remember? Shma yisroe, yes, I remember that too.
But, uh, it was learned, wasn't it?
Only because I sang it very often, er, on holidays, my brother and I, it stuck a bit.
But it was always very nice and... They were, they were comrades. And the women.
We used to fool around in the synagogue. We were always behind laurel trees.
Mmm. My God. There was a Berlin, uh, margarine representative who was laughing.
He said: "I can't sing that if, if, if, if, if I'm hungry.
I have to acheln." Right? That was all. They were all very nice.
Do you, uh, yes, do you, uh, believe in God, do you? Do I believe in God? Yes.
I believe in my wife. Hm. If you like. Mhm.
And musically, it's, uh, Gustav Mahler for me. Hm.
And do you have these, uh, songs and also, uh, these prayers, they say? Yes.
Did you, when you experienced difficulties late in the Third Reich?
Did you think about these songs and- No. prayers? No, no, no.
Did you say the Shma in Russia? No, never. No.
You know, the struggle for existence, for survival
was the only thing that clung to your consciousness. Nothing.
Not thinking left and right, not looking left and right, but holding on to survival, man.
Yes? Can you imagine that? Not being able to wash your hands for eight weeks?
No toilet? Only snow? Well. And what did you eat? Cold rations.
But not, uh-- When we were under fire, the assholes didn't even dare to come to us.
We had to wait until the next day for the rations to arrive and all that.
We were all given this so-called rubber sausage. That was a hunting sausage.
And, uh, yes, what else did we get? Oh, some canned meat. All cold.
Never a hot meal. Only cold.
And chocolate cola to keep us brave and, and, and, uh, cognac.
But not in quantities, of course. Mmm. And where did you sleep?
Yes, in the-- I told you earlier, in the grenade funnel.
We had lined it with blankets. Mhm. And was it possible to sleep there?
Of course it was. You wouldn't believe what a person can go through.
Young, above all, healthy. Yes. (sings) Oh, where is she? Howo? It hurts.
It hurts. Uh. Oh, God. Well, something like that.
(laughs) El hoo adonai, Elohenu. Yes. (laughs) Oh, just please, go on.
No, no, no. That's all right. I've had enough now. But I'm glad you found this.
You know the-- Shall I tell you? Yes, briefly. Yes, a quick question, yes.
What's your name? Can you say your name? My name is Peter Wilhelm Tescher.
Just a moment. What is your father's name? My father's name was Wilhelm Tescher.
And how did you find out about your Jewish ancestry? How did I find out?
Actually, um, from my father's stories, um, which had a lot to do with his time as a soldier.
And I held a piece of paper in my hand when I was relatively young.
It was this key experience where it said that my father was allowed to become an officer with a special permit from Adolf Hitler.
And, um - it was just a permit? It was a special permit. But not a license.
No, no. No, no. Just a permit. It said, I can give you a copy of it again.
Maybe we'll just make a list of the things I bring over to you.
Um, it says on it that I reserve the right to make a final decision after the war.
Hm. That's one story, the other story-- of course we asked: Why was that?
And the other story is that during the war my father went to Bialystok
which was occupied by the Germans at the time
and tried to get an official certificate stating that only one of his parents
his mother, i.e. his maternal grandparent, was of Jewish descent.
There were no more documents about this and he actually came back with this certificate from an official from this administration.
And that, uh, was then also, yes half a life insurance policy for my grandmother
who- So actually both grandparents were Jewish? I don't know...
Well, the certificate says only one parent.
But what did your father say about that? Uh, he was, um...
He probably didn't know himself that-- Uh
the story is that after the First World War
my grandfather was also called Wilhelm Tescher
after the First World War in 1917, after the Peace of Brest-Litovsk, uh
administrator of a large sawmill of the German army administration-- What was his name?
Wilhelm Tescher too, yes. Also. First World War, yes
he was the manager of a large sawmill belonging to the German army administration in the
uh, in the then, uh, German-occupied territories near Bialystok.
And in the nineteen hundreds - I think they had to leave there in 1919 after the capitulation.
And then, right? And he brought a young woman with him from there.
That was my grandmother.
Her name was, um, Frida Sobonitzky, she was Russian of German descent and nineteen years old.
My grandfather was thirty-nine and my father the first-born son of this marriage
was born in Germany at the age of nineteen.
And my grandfather then took over my parents' small sawmill, a very small sawmill.
And this, uh, sawmill continued to run. My grandmother was here.
There was contact with the family in Russia until the nineteen hundreds
until the early thirties, and then Stalin resettled everyone.
And since then there has been no sign of life from this part of the family.
Well, actually, it's not known, uh
that another brother of my grandmother was in Berlin again around nineteen thirties
as far as I've been told, and met with, with, with relatives, yes.
But there's no longer any connection to this, to these grandparents, to these relatives.
Uh, the grandmother was there too and didn't see that as a problem with us.
And with the seizure of power came difficulties for my father.
He wasn't allowed to get married to Wedern
he wasn't allowed to-- There were also difficulties with school.
He then changed schools and couldn't do his Abitur.
Hm.quarry with us, which incidentally was built in the Westwall.
If the Jewish grandmother, she was born... You can look that up.
We have a proof of ancestry, but I don't have it with me now. I can also...
I'll write down what I... Or is she writing? Yes, I'll write it down.
So that I can give you this...
Yes, every document is very important if you have a lot of documents out there.
Yes. Well, that would be the proof of ancestry, I have that somewhere.
The authorization. Yes, so this history.
And my grandmother isn't in any danger, at least not for the time being
because my family is very respected.
Although in a neighboring village a whole bunch of Jews got away
but my grandmother, that was somewhere, that's how it was.
There were no problems. Only my father had some problems.
My father then became a soldier in 1939, took part in the French campaign
in the first attacks, and after the French campaign he rejoined the pioneers.
He had huge casualties in the first few days.
He was with the first river pioneers.
Then he came back to Mainz in the Galisodes and later, after the coal addiction...
This is now a Mr. Hossen. Am I in the right place?
I'm in the right place, right? Yes, yes. I have... Mr.
Brosset, Lieutenant Janzen. I just want to put something here for Mrs. Schümmer.
Here you are. I was looking for you. You were at emart. Don't worry.
My father went with me to Russia when they went out.
He was always in the front line and also received forty-two German Gold.
And what did he get it for?
We didn't talk much about direct war-related measures.
I only know that my father led the remnants of a pioneer battalion out of the fighting for weeks
or at least for days, as an Obergfreiter at the time and, among other things
I believe, in connection with a serious injury to his commander.
He's still alive, by the way. I can give you his name.
Maybe you should talk to him on the phone.
He was his commander for many years afterwards. That's Schmischkel.
I think he was also a colonel, or I don't know.
So Schmichkel, Helmut Schmichkel. And I'll write it down for you, the address.
And did her sibling, Father, also get permission from Hinter? No.
So there were two sisters and a brother and the brother was also a soldier.
What was the brother's name? Fritz Brescher.
Lives in Kloster Reichenbach near Freudenstadt here at Vogelherd.
If he can't be reached there, he can be contacted via the Tröscher and Beilharz company.
But we can organize that somehow later.
As far as I know, Franz Tröscher was a prisoner for a long time.
He had probably become a sergeant, a paymaster or something.
I think the Russians kept the paymasters for a long time.
Somehow he only came back from captivity at the beginning of the fifties.
And then he took over the sawmill at home and is now also a timber merchant here in Freudenstadt.
Yes, and my father then... Then he was suggested...
So his superiors tried to get him to become an officer.
And then, on the one hand... Well
I don't remember exactly whether this certificate from Bialostock was needed at home to protect my grandmother or rather so that he could do an officer's course.
In any case, with this special permit from Hitler, which I just...
These are simpler files.
So it only says Hitler, but it was actually decided by Hitler himself
he was able to attend the officers' course in Dessau, completed this course
as far as I know, as the best of the course
then also experienced Hitler up close for the first time at the end
at the end of this course, because Hitler himself passed this course, in 1943.
Really? Yes, he went to Dessau, flew and said goodbye to this course.
That was the last, probably the last.
And then after a relatively short time he probably became a lieutenant and was then transferred from Russia to Italy and was back on the Russian front in the last days of the war.
But we didn't actually talk that much about the war itself.
It was more of a fundamental thing.
And as a first lieutenant in the American, but then British...
I think the Americans did it in England or something
so he was an English prisoner and then - he was back home very early
was of course unencumbered
he actually came out as a convinced pacifist after the crisis
but he was also a realist
he first rebuilt the sawmill and then joined the KPD back then
so he was a communist
and after a relatively short time he took over the mayor's post in our town on a temporary basis and then
at the age of twenty-eight, in 1948
he was also elected mayor of the municipality or district.
That was his entry into politics.
Then he was fifty-five in the state parliament, fifty-seven in the Bundestag
the European Parliament, and then, well, he became Federal Chancellor.
And was your father proud of this German cross and gold?
Uh, I think my father was everywhere he was in his life, he tried to make the best of it.
I think he was, yes, I think he was someone who, you know, with everyone.
He was always very much, very gladly and very quickly responsible for other people.
And that is of course also in the long war
regardless of whether you think he was unjust or just, um
it's an ability that comes through very quickly. So
he was a leader in every respect and I believe that this bravery was not something that was purely personal
yes, to gain honor
but that in this situation he also took matters into his own hands for others and
of course, for himself.
Yes, I believe that he tackled everything in his life with great courage.
And it's hard to judge that.
I myself was a soldier in the Bundeswehr, er, in peacetime.
And it's very difficult to judge, um, how this situation, this war
is always progressing, that your friend the pioneers, yes, a lot
have had a lot of losses, how that affects your attitude to life.
So you always had the feeling that he dealt with danger very calmly.
Even afterwards, I have to say, with the threat that he knew, um, his own
his own difficult life situation, uh, no situation at all.
He worked until the end and then died in Hamburg at an SPD party conference shortly before he was due to give a speech.
(sighs) Yes, so it's, it's changed a lot, this, this wartime.
I think he once wrote, perhaps I can also find this
that it was only in this situation
in which he experienced Hitler so closely in 1943
that he knew from that moment on that this man was crazy
that this man was a madman and that a catastrophe
which one certainly already suspected
but from that moment on he probably knew that this catastrophe could no longer
could no longer be contained. So, what did he think about his permit?
(sighs) Well, signed by Hitler, the mercy of the Führer.
So I don't think that my father, that my father's Jewish origins played a role.
My father was always a citizen of the world, even as a young man, when I didn't yet know him.
Even as a secondary school pupil, he read English and French newspapers
spoke five or six languages fluently
tried to learn a bit of Russian through these relatives
but I don't think that this idea of being Jewish played any role at all.
Uh, that, well, I don't think so. Did you... Yes.
Yes, did you lose any relatives in the Holocaust? No. Well, not in Germany.
My grandmother was the only one who came over.
We certainly lost relatives, but we don't know that, through Stalin's deportation.
Mmm. Yes. So in that respect, we're not, we're certainly not the typical, uh
family that lived in Germany with Jewish relatives.
It was just my grandmother, who was also...
The authorities didn't want to know exactly whether she was of half or quarter or full Jewish descent.
Mhm.
That-- But my uncle, who lived through that time, can probably tell you a lot more about that.
(crosstalk 00:04:48) And your father's friend, who wrote to me
said that your father said that his Jewish grandmother was completely Jewish.
It could be, it could be. Well, we didn't really talk much about that.
Uh, about-- you, well, it didn't really matter to us whether she was completely...
It was important that he got this certificate, but for us, uh, it's
and that's the same for us today, so, we're, um-our country.
We are aware of that. We've always been a country where cultures have mixed.
Where we come from, Roman influences are still very much in evidence.
And the progenitor, the first thresher, can be traced back to the Thirty Years' War.
I'll come back to that, also with genealogical research
he was a Swedish mercenary who came to Germany with Gustav Adolf and then got stuck with us
so he married an impostor. So for us
I would say that having Jewish ancestors is neither something to do with pride nor something to do with shame.
It's something that actually comes quite naturally to us.
We are six siblings and I think we all feel that way and yes
that's what I can actually tell you now. Doing something for people.
I also don't believe that he committed any atrocities without need or anything.
He was actually too human for that.
But war is an exceptional situation and I can't imagine it for someone who isn't war-minded.
You probably feel the same way. I do.
It's a situation that you only really know if you've experienced it.
Did he learn about the Holocaust back then?
I assume that at least from 1943 onwards, 44 would have been aware of some things there too.
I assume that. But. Difficult. Difficult to say. Did he talk about it?
He actually only talked about it.
After the war, he was always very consciously against.
For example, as state chairman of the SPD, which he was a strong voice
he chaired the parliamentary group in the state parliament.
In Mainz, he did not attend American receptions during the Vietnam War
which he considered to be an unjust war, which was a huge scandal.
So he had a lot of self-confidence and moral courage when he thought that injustice was being done.
And then he did. He didn't stand up for himself, he didn't do it.
He didn't go there and he wrote to them to explain why he wasn't coming.
And that's in a state like Rhineland-Palatinate.
There was a huge uproar and scandal that someone didn't go to see his American friends.
He did things like that. He was affected by these experiences after the war.
I think it was more of a reinforcement or an imprint on his personality
which then developed after the war.
I was born shortly after the war and I witnessed a lot of people who then expressed themselves in such a way that he really fought very
very hard for peace, for justice, for social justice, for development
for international understanding and so on
that we can actually talk about very personal experiences in the war
which I'm sure we did. You can't survive a war like that without feeling guilty.
I don't think that's possible. But we never really talked about that.
I believe that his personality was shaped by these experiences
which he ultimately classified as terrible
but which he faced up to as the person he was by trying to become a hero. Yes.
They didn't come about because he somehow only ever stood up for a just cause
but because you make decisions and take things into your own hands in situations where your own life and the lives of your comrades are at stake.
And I assume that it was more this imprint that played a role later on
which was the sum of the experiences during the war.
There is a brochure from the political period that also contains a bit about the war.
I will enclose it when I send it to you. Before we talk about your list.
Can you tell me your name? What is your name? Friedrich Christian Stahl.
When were you born? On October 28, 1918 in Berlin.
And you talked about Labram a bit earlier.
How did you know that Heinrich Labram had experienced so many problems?
We were both together.
We were both heads of department at the Military History Research Office
so we often spoke to each other and also socialized with each other.
And what did he say about his experience in the Kriegsmarine?
Paraprophe came out and the Jewish officers who had not taken part in the First World War were to be excluded from the Wehrmacht.
In his case
it was particularly tragic because his brother had already crashed after 1933 or in 1933 as a trained aviation officer.
When the question came to him, he himself asked to speak to his high commander, Admiral Raeder.
He was refused. And he was very angry about that.
After the war, did he try to have a court case with ??? did he?
I don't think so. He didn't talk about that either.
I think we've finished the Lebram case. Then I spoke about Österreicher.
Österreicher was a lieutenant in motorized division seven, which was in Munich.
And- From the first name, you know? I don't know.
You know, the first name never played a role in the German army.
Or let's say in the Prussian, in the Bavarian, yes. Okay.
(Laughter) I only know the case and I know that Österreicher survived the war.
Hm. That's all I can say. And he had been with your father?
How did you know that he was an officer candidate with my father, i.e.
as an ensign and midshipman at the infantry school.
My father was a teacher for the midshipmen, i.e.
for the second course at the infantry school
and that's how I got to know all of them - there were only ten of them for the motorized troops
for example. And what was going on with him?
Did he have a Jewish parent or big ones? I don't know that.
I only knew him until he was nineteen thirty-one or thirty-two and not after that.
And ah yes, was, did he get a declaration of German blood?
How was it possible that he stayed in the German Wehrmacht?
No, no, he didn't get a declaration of German blood, because he had to leave.
So he was discharged first? Yes. The next one?
Yes, then there are some cases where I just want to say the name.
I'm sure you're familiar with these cases. I've already said Backenköhler. Mhm.
You will of course be familiar with Wilberg. Milk. And Backenköhler.
You have an interesting story about the naval adjutant.
I remember that either Raeder's adjutant or a personnel officer or the head of the naval personnel office came to Raeder and drew his attention to the order that naval officers of Jewish descent had to be dismissed.
And Raeder is said to have said
"That doesn't concern the navy." To which the man in question replied, "But Mr.
Admiral," and mentioned several names, including Backenköhler. Hm.
I can't say any more about that.
It was all a very long time ago that I heard that and I don't remember who said it.
Mhm. Then there was the case of General Kühntal, military attaché in Paris.
Kühlintal? Kühlintal, yes. Ah The admiral?
The admiral is, if I'm not mistaken, a brother of his. I see.
Yes, he came out of the war mine in nineteen-twenty.